Robert B. Brigham Hospital. Records, 1889–1984 (Bulk 1915–1980): Finding Aid.
Records, 1889–1984 (Bulk 1915–1980).
Francis A. Countway Library of Medicine. Center for the History of Medicine.
BWH c4
Robert B. Brigham Hospital
7 cubic feet in 6 record cartons, 2 flat document boxes, and 1 map drawer.
Robert B. Brigham Hospital Records, 1889–1984 (Bulk 1915–1980), are the product of the hospital staff’s administrative, fundraising, publications, training programs, legal proceedings, and public relations activities from 1915 through 1980.
Robert B. Brigham Hospital records were transferred from the Brigham and Women’s Hospital Medical Library to the Harvard Medical Library in 2005. Additional material was added as follows:
Accession number 2007–006 was transferred from the Brigham and Women’s Hospital Medical Library to the Harvard Medical Library in July, 2006.
Brigham and Women’s Hospital (BWH) owns the records described in this finding aid. The Harvard Medical Library entered into a contract in 2005 to act as the repository for some of BWH’s archival records. Before the transfer to the Harvard Medical Library in 2005, the records were in storage at various locations within the BWH and later collected and assembled for transfer by Anne Fladger, Director of the BWH Medical Library.
Access requires advance notice. Access to unpublished administrative records is restricted for 50 years from creation date. Access to personal and patient information is restricted for 80 years from creation date. Restricted records, except restricted patient photographs, are noted in the finding aid. Student records are restricted until the death of the student. Researchers may apply for access to restricted material. Consult the Director of Brigham and Women’s Hospital Medical Library for further information. (Email: BWHMedicalLibrary@partners.org.)
Related Collections in the Francis A. Countway Library of Medicine, Center for the History of Medicine.
Brigham and Women’s Hospital. Records, 1900– (Bulk 1980–2000). [BWH c1]
Affiliated Hospitals Center (Boston, Mass.) Records, 1966–1984. [BWH c2]
Peter Bent Brigham Hospital. Records, 1907–1992. [BWH c3]
Boston Hospital for Women. Records, 1926–1983 (Bulk 1966–1979). Records. [BWH c5]
Free Hospital for Women. Records, 1875–1975. [BWH c6]
Free Hospital for Women. Records, 1879–1969. [MC 915]
Boston Lying-in Hospital. Records, 1855–1983 (Bulk 1921–1966). [BWH c7]
Series and Subseries in the Collection
Series I. Program Establishment, Development, and Review Records, 1903–1976.
Series II. Committee Records, 1915–1984.
Series III. Legal Proceedings and Investigation Records, 1924–1954.
Series IV. Human Resources Program Records, 1953.
Series V. Special Event Records 1935, 1944.
Series VI. Robert B. Brigham School for Attendant Nurses, Student Records, 1923–1951.
Series VII. Fundraising Campaign Records, circa 1920s–circa 1970s.
Series VIII. Public Relations Records, 1951–1975.
Series IX. Publications, 1954–1978.
Series X. Photographs, circa 1950s–circa 1980.
Series XI. Memorabilia, 1959–1961.
Series XII. Resource and Reference Materials, 1889–1984.
Historical Notes
The Robert B. Brigham Hospital for Incurables, established via the philanthropic legacy of Robert Breck Brigham at the beginning of the 20th century, became the first American teaching hospital devoted exclusively to the care of arthritis and rheumatic disease. Coming of age during a time of far-reaching changes in the role of the modern hospital and patient care, “The Robert” matured into the Division of Rheumatology, Immunology and Allergy in the Department of Medicine of Brigham and Women’s Hospital, a teaching affiliate of Harvard Medical School, by the beginning of the 21st century.
The intention to create a free hospital for poor citizens with chronic or incurable diseases was articulated in the will of Robert Breck Brigham in 1900. Like his uncle Peter Bent Brigham, Robert Brigham made his fortune as a restaurant owner and real estate developer. And similar to his uncle, whose endowment founded the Peter Bent Brigham Hospital, Robert bequeathed the majority of his estate to several charities. A trust was established to use part of his bequest for the creation of a hospital for the “…medical and surgical treatment of those citizens of Boston who are …incapable of obtaining a comfortable livelihood by reason of chronic or incurable disease or permanent physical disability.”
Elizabeth Fay Brigham, Robert’s sister and the director of the corporation organized to create the hospital, died in 1909 adding one-and-a-half million dollars of her estate towards the construction. Although the Robert B. Brigham Hospital for Incurables was chartered in 1903, and 10 acres of land was purchased as a building site on top of Mission Hill in Boston in 1905, the construction was not completed until 1914.
The hospital opened on April 1, 1914 for admissions with 115 beds, and soon thereafter began to focus on those patients with arthritis and rheumatic diseases—well before rheumatology was a recognized medical specialty. “Incurable” patients received free care and many remained in the hospital for months without charge. Advances in medical technology, surgical repair of deformities, and drugs to manage inflammation, all tested and put into practice over the years at the Robert B. Brigham Hospital, led to more and more of the formerly “incurable” patients resuming normal or near normal functioning in their daily lives. Success led to an increase in requests for treatment. The mounting monetary burden of providing free care for poor patients exceeded the income from the Brigham legacy and financial pressures constantly threatened the hospital’s survival.
In 1917 the hospital was leased by the government for the care of sick and wounded military personnel, causing a suspension of the Robert B. Brigham Hospital’s normal operations and scattering the staff. The suspension paradoxically led to a financial reprieve for the struggling hospital and it was reopened in 1923.
The successful treatment of many chronically ill patients and the hospital’s need for more income than that provided by the Brigham charitable trust led to the practice of admitting some paying patients. A lawsuit in 1925 resulted from a claim by one of the hospital’s trustees that treating curable patients and taking paying patients violated the stipulations of the Brigham will. By court decree in July of 1926 the argument that Robert B. Brigham’s intention was to create an “old-folks home,” not a paying hospital or a research hospital, failed in favor of the other trustees’ interpretations that allowed them to treat patients who did have hope for a cure, and to admit some paying patients. Declining income in the 1930s caused the beginning of the end of free care and the idea of the hospital as primarily a charity. To avoid closing the hospital, private paying patients were cultivated. By 1949 all patients were charged for the cost of their care.
It was not until another court proceeding in 1954 that the “for Incurables” was legally dropped from the name of the hospital, although the term had not been not used for many years.
Significant practices in the rheumatology specialty evolved at the Robert B. Brigham Hospital, including the use of cortisone to manage rheumatoid arthritis and the notion of having separate occupational and physical therapy departments. The Robert B. Brigham Hospital established the first hospital based occupational therapy department. Orthopedic nursing was professionalized at the Robert. B. Brigham Training School for Attendant Nurses. This school produced licensed practical nurses from 1924 through 1951. Sub-specialties, including neurology, ophthalmology, dermatology, roentgenology, pharmacy, artificial joints, documentation standards, and community outreach, as related to orthopedics and rheumatology, were rooted and grew in importance in the research departments, clinics, and wards of Robert B. Brigham Hospital. As a teaching hospital, the Robert B. Brigham had close ties with the doctors and patients of the Peter Bent Brigham, Massachusetts General, Children’s, and the Beth Israel Hospitals. By 1944 the relationship between the Robert B. Brigham Hospital and the Peter Bent Brigham Hospital had formalized with a rotation for residents at the Robert B. Brigham Hospital. In 1966, the Robert B. Brigham Hospital became an official Harvard teaching hospital.
The Robert B. Brigham Hospital’s mission and evolution were shaped for over 60 years by many noted individuals, among them, medically progressive orthopedic surgeon, Joel E. Goldthwait (1866–1961), one of the original trustees of the corporation, who guided the hospital towards a progressive (at the time) philosophy of multidisciplinary approaches to treating, not just symptoms, but patients as a whole, considering their family and social context, and their post-discharge well-being; and chief orthopedic surgeon (1917-1935) Loring T. Swaim, who brought a psychosocial approach to patient care and established an arthritis clinic at the Robert B. Brigham Hospital. Other notable “firsts” to practice and teach in the new specialty of rheumatology were Theodore B. Bayles, appointed to head a permanent research program in 1939, and Sydney Stillman, who along with Goldthwait, organized the Clinical Treatment Center for Juvenile Rheumatoid Arthritis in 1963, a prototype in the field for other specialized services for children. Arthur Hall and Peter Barry were early clinician teachers at the Robert B. Brigham Hospital who deeply influenced the following generations of rheumatologists, including Ronald J. Anderson, Director of Clinical Training Programs from 1971 to 2003. Also in the modern era, Clement B. Sledge, Chief of Orthopedic Surgery, was a pioneer in joint replacement surgery; and Physician-in-Chief, K. Frank Austen, played a central role in the merger that created what is known today as the Brigham and Women’s Hospital. His team elevated the Robert B. Brigham Hospital immunology research program to international stature by working out the key mechanisms of allergy and inflammation.
In 1975 the era of the small specialty hospital in Boston ended when the Robert B. Brigham Hospital merged with the Peter Bent Brigham Hospital and the Boston Hospital for Women forming the Affiliated Hospitals Center. (Boston Hospital for Women itself was the result of a 1966 merger of the Boston Lying-in Hospital with the Free Hospital for Women.) In 1980, at the time of the opening of a new state-of-the-art facility, the Affiliated Hospitals Center became known as the Brigham and Women’s Hospital, a teaching affiliate of the Harvard Medical School. The original buildings of the Robert B. Brigham Hospital located at the top of Mission Hill in Boston, as of this writing, are part of the New England Baptist Hospital complex.
Brigham and Women’s Hospital. “Celebrating the BWH Heritage.” BWH 1996, Brigham and Women’s Hospital, Fall, 1996.
Brigham and Women’s Hospital. “Rheumatology, Immunology and Allergy, History of the Division.” Brigham and Women’s Hospital, 2008. http://www.brighamandwomens.org/rheumatology/history.aspx?subID=submenu1
J.G.K., “Joel Ernest Goldthwait 1866–1961,” The Journal of Bone and Joint Surgery, The Journal of Bone and Joint Surgery, Inc. Needham MA, April 1, 1961. http://www.ejbjs.org/cgi/reprint/43/3/463
Liang, Matthew H. A Short History of the Robert B. Brigham Hospital (1916–1980). Pre-publication draft, Brigham and Women’s Hospital, 2007.
Rachelefsky, Lance. “On Trust and Playing the Best Hand: A Conversation with K. Frank Austen, MD.” Your Medicine Online, Brigham and Women’s Hospital, (February, 2005). http://www.brighamandwomens.org/dom_newsletter/February_05/FrankAusten.htm
Robert B. Brigham Hospital. Robert B. Brigham Hospital, Parker Hill Avenue, Boston, Mass., Office: Eighteen Tremont St. Robert B. Brigham Hospital, Boston, 1923.
Robert B. Brigham Hospital. Fifty Years of Service. Annual review booklet, 1964. Robert B. Brigham Hospital records, 1889–1984 (Bulk 1915–1980). BWH c4. Harvard Medical Library, Francis A. Countway Library of Medicine, Boston, Mass.
Legal Proceedings and Investigation Records, Robert B. Brigham Hospital records, 1889–1984 (Bulk 1915–1980). BWH c4. Harvard Medical Library, Francis A. Countway Library of Medicine, Boston, Mass.
Scope and Content
The records of the Robert B. Brigham Hospital consist of those generated by the staff of the institution while conducting administrative business and public outreach from 1915 through 1975, and those generated by the staff of the Robert B. Brigham Division of the Affiliated Hospitals Center after the 1975 merger. Material in the collection dated before 1915 includes a limited number of journal articles written by staff members. The records dated after 1980 include meeting minutes of the Robert B. Brigham Hospital board of trustees, who continued to meet after the merger and after the integration in 1980 of the three hospital divisions into the unified Brigham and Women’s Hospital.
Included in the records are annual reports, meeting minutes and agendas, memoranda, committee records, and transcripts of legal proceedings related to interpreting the intentions of Robert B. Brigham’s will. The collection also contains the microfilmed student records from the Robert B. Brigham School for Attendant Nurses. Additional records include press releases, programs, newspaper clippings, copies of serial and stock publications, and the visual material used to create publications. The photographs among the visual materials include images of staff, patients, hospital events, and buildings. Many of the photographs depict staff and patients actively engaged in physical therapy. Other than limited patient photographs, there are no patient records in the collection.
Box and Folder Lists
- I. Program Establishment, Development and Review Records, 1903–1976., (26 folders/items and 1 oversize item.)
  Contains annual reports and annual meeting minutes which review major hospital or department organization, activities, functions, programs, and policies. Professional staff by-laws and auditor’s reports are included within this series.
  - (Box 1: Folders/Items 1–16.)
    - Corporation Documents, 1903, 1954., 1.; Includes a 1954 copy of the 1903 Agreement of Association, and 1954 Certificate of Incorporation, Change of Purpose forms, and amended by-laws.
    - Corporation Records, Annual Meeting Minutes, 1922–1942., 2.
    - Corporation Records, Annual Meeting Minutes, 1943–1954., 3.
    - Corporation Records, Annual Meeting Minutes, 1954–1959., 4.
    - Corporation Records, Annual Meeting Minutes, 1960–1962., 5.
    - Corporation Records, Annual Meeting Minutes, 1963–1964., 6.
    - Corporation Records, Annual Meeting Minutes, 1965–1966., 7.
    - Corporation Records, Annual Meeting Minutes, 1967–1969. (Bound volume.), 8.
    - Corporation Records, Annual Meeting Minutes, 1970–1973. (Bound volume.), 9.
    - Corporation Records, Annual Meeting Minutes, 1974–1976. (Bound volume.), 10.
    - Annual Reports, 1918, 1924–1925, 1927–1930., 11.
    - Annual Reports, 1951–1955., 12.
    - Annual Reports, 1956–1957., 13.
    - Annual Reports, 1961–1962., 14.
    - Annual Reports, 1964–1965., 15.
    - Annual Report, 1966., 16.
  - (Box 2: Folders/Items 1–11.)
    - Annual Reports, 1961–1967. (Bound volume.), 1.
    - Annual Reports, 1968–1974. (Bound volume.), 2.
    - Annual Reports, 1967–1968., 3.
    - Annual Reports, 1969–1970., 4.
    - Annual Reports, 1971–1972., 5.
    - Annual Report, 1973., 6.
    - Annual Report, 1975., 7.
    - Annual Report, 1976., 8.
    - Medical Staff By-Laws, 1967–1972., 9.
    - Corporation By-Laws and Articles, 1916., 10.
    - Auditors’ Reports, 1969–1971., 11.
  - (Map Drawer XL03)
    - Accreditation Certificate from Joint Commission on Accreditation of Hospitals,1978., 1.; Oversized item.
- II. Committee Records, 1915–1984., (1 record carton, 1 folder.)
  Contains large bound volumes of the minutes of meetings of the board of directors, overseers, and trustees; and various sub-committees including those on investments, public and community relations, budget planning, personnel and compensation. Also includes the 1915–1918 reports of the Social Services Committee, the hospital’s de facto social workers, responsible for the admission and discharge of charity patients.
  - (Box 2: Folder 20.)
    - The Social Services Committee of the Robert B. Brigham Hospital, Reports, 1915–1918.; 20.; This notebook, formerly on display, is in fragile condition. It contains several loose, handwritten note pages in addition to the notebook pages. Also includes two pages of historical recollections about the Social Service Committee written in 1948.
  - (Box 3: Items 1–9.)
    - Minutes, Director’s Meetings, volume IV, 1958–1963., 1.
      Restricted until 2013.
    - Directors Records, 1916–1921., 2.
    - Directors Records, 1921–1934., 3.
    - Minutes, Director’s Meetings, volume V, 1969., 4.
      Restricted until 2019.
    - Minutes, Director’s Meetings, volume VI, 1972., 5.
      Restricted until 2022.
    - Minutes, Director’s Meetings, volume VII, 1973., 6.
      Restricted until 2023.
    - Minutes, Board Meetings, volume VIII, 1975., 7.
      Restricted until 2025.
    - Minutes, Board Meetings, volume IX, 1976., 8.
      Restricted until 2026.
    - Minutes, Board Meetings, volume X, 1978–1984., 9.
      Restricted until 2034.
- III. Legal Proceedings and Investigation Records, 1924–1954., (5 folders/items.)
  Contains legal documents, court proceedings transcripts, and correspondence in bound volumes concerning a lawsuit brought against the officers of Robert B. Brigham Hospital for Incurables for allegedly “misusing and misapplying the funds of the estate of the late Robert Breck Brigham…” in the 1920s. Also includes legal documents and correspondence from the 1950s related to Robert B. Brigham Hospital’s application to the courts to drop “for Incurables” from the official hospital name, and seeking relief from the restrictive provisions set forth in Robert Breck Brigham’s will concerning types of admissible patients, required Boston residency, and uses of the hospital’s income.
  - (Box 2: Folders/Items 12–15.)
    - Request of the City of Boston that the Attorney-General Bring an Information Against the Robert B. Brigham Hospital: Testimony, Volume I, 1924–1925., 12.
    - Request of the City of Boston that the Attorney-General Bring an Information Against the Robert B. Brigham Hospital: Testimony, Volume II, 1924–1925., 13.
    - Dillaway vs. Burton, et al and R. B. Brigham Hospital vs. Attorney-General: Records, Briefs, Opinions and Decrees, 1925–1926., 14.
    - Robert B. Brigham Hospital for Incurables: Report of the Legal Committee, 1949., 15.
  - (Box 6: Folder 1.)
    - Cy Pres Proceedings, 1953–1954., 1.; Oversize. Formerly Box 2, Folder 16.
- IV. Human Resources Program Records, 1953., (1 folder.)
  - (Box 2: Folder 17.)
    - Handbook for Personnel, 1953., 17.
- V. Special Event Records, 1935, 1944., (2 folders.)
  Includes the program for a benefit performance of a play given at the Hollis Street Theatre by the Abbey Theatre Players on their 1935 American tour, and a printed copy of The Robert B. Brigham Team Song.
  - (Box 2: Folders 18–19.)
    - Benefit Performance, Drama at Inish, 1935., 18.
    - The Robert B. Brigham Team Song, 1944., 19.; Words and music by Richard M. Hadden.
- VI. Robert B. Brigham School for Attendant Nurses, Student Records, 1923–1951.; (2 rolls of microfilm.)
  These are the microfilmed copies of student records, including applications, grades, teachers’ evaluations, and dates of graduation, resignation, or dismissal.
  Records were filmed in alphabetical order by student’s last name.
  Access to student records is restricted until the death of the student.
  - (Box 4: Items 30–31.)
    - Robert B. Brigham Hospital Training School, Students (A–M), 1923–1951; 30.; microfilm.
    - Robert B. Brigham Hospital Training School, Students (N–Z), 1923–1951; 31.; microfilm.
- VII. Fundraising Campaign Records, circa 1920s–circa 1970s., (2 folders.)
  - (Box 4: Folders 1–2.)
    - Fundraising Campaign Pamphlets, circa 1920s–circa 1970s., 1.
    - Fundraising Campaign Pamphlets, circa 1960s–circa 1970s., 2.
- VIII. Public Relations Records, 1951–1975., (3 folders.)
  Includes records produced from Robert B. Brigham Hospital’s efforts to promote an effective and cooperative working relationship with the general public. Contains copies of printed publicity materials, and newspaper clippings and journal photocopies of subjects related to Robert B. Brigham Hospital. One folder of clippings and photocopies is dedicated to the uses of aspirin as a treatment for arthritis.
  - (Box 4: Folders 3–5.)
    - Publicity, 1958., 3.
    - Clippings, 1951–1974., 4.
    - Subject File: Aspirin, 1963–1975., 5.
- IX. Publications, 1954–1978., (16 folders.)
  Contains issues of The Piper, a newsletter published by the Office of Public relations with contributions from the hospital staff. The archives holds an incomplete set of issues from Winter 1966–Winter 1969/1970. Also contains copies of RBBH Forum, a bi-monthly newsletter created by personnel of the Robert B. Brigham Hospital as “information for members.” The archives holds issues from December of 1970 through November of 1977. It is unknown if further issues of RBBH Forum were published after this time range. Also included in this series are 3 issues of a single-sheet bulletin, RBBH News Bulletin, published by the Public Relations Department in 1977 and 1978. Other serial publications include the RBBH for Arthritis and Rheumatic Diseases Report, from 1971–1976, a “publication designed to keep friends of the hospital informed…” and the Annual Review Booklet from 1957–1973, serving as an abridged annual report. Non-serial items include stock publications such as brochures, announcements, directories, patient guides, pamphlets, etc.
  - (Box 4: Folders 6–21.)
    - RBBH Forum,1970., 6.; Issue 1.
    - RBBH Forum, 1971., 7.; Issues 2–6.
    - RBBH Forum, 1972., 8.; Issues 7–11.
    - RBBH Forum,1973., 9.; Issues 12–15.
    - RBBH Forum, 1974., 10.; Issues 17–18. (Missing issue 16.)
    - RBBH Forum,1975., 11.; Issues 20–22. (Missing issue 19.)
    - RBBH Forum,1976., 12.; Issues 23–26, and June Special Issue.
    - RBBH Forum, 1977., 13.; Issues 27–29, and July Special Issue.
    - The Piper, 1966–1970., 14.
    - RBBH News Bulletin, 1977–1978., 15.; Folder includes one formally printed memo for staff about handling syringes safely.
    - Stock Publications, 1975–1977., 16.
    - Stock Publications, 1954–1975., 17.
    - RBBH for Arthritis and Rheumatic Diseases Report,1972–1976., 18.
    - RBBH for Arthritis and Rheumatic Diseases Report,1971–1976., 19.
    - Annual Review booklets, 1957–1962., 20.
    - Annual Review booklets, 1963–1973., 21.
- X. Photographs, circa 1950s–circa 1980., (1 record carton, 2 flat document boxes.)
  This series consists primarily of black and white photographic prints used or maintained for possible inclusion in hospital publications, newsletters, and press releases. The photographs include images of staff, patients, hospital events, and buildings. Many of the photographs depict staff and patients actively engaged in physical therapy. There are some contact sheets, slides, negatives, color snapshots, and printing layout materials included. Not all of the images are identified or dated. Images in the collection obviously depicting pre-1950s scenes are all modern (circa 1970s) copy prints of original photographs, now lost.
  Arranged by subject.
  - (Box 5: Folders 1–44.)
    - Ladies Auxiliary, 1963–1969., 1.
    - Engineering/Maintenance, 1962–1975., 2.
    - 1960–1969 Special Events, 1960–1969., 3.
    - Housekeeping, 1975., 4.